Guide to the Collection of Book Illustrations
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of book illustrations
1793-1999
AOB 75
Yale University Arts Library
1.67
(4 boxes)
This collection comprises illustrations salvaged from damaged bound volumes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Collection of Book Illustrations was housed in the former Arts of the Book Collection until its transfer to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises illustrations salvaged from damaged bound volumes. Thus, many plates are lacking for each publication.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. English. II. French. III. German.
The materials are arranged by language (of publication or publisher). If known, the publication is identified. Otherwise, a description of the subject matter identifies the materials.
Illustration of books; Chromolithographs; Intaglio prints -- Color; Intaglio prints
- English, Series I
  - [adventures of "Christian," possibly illustrations of The Pilgrim's Progress ] by Henry Moses (plates 1-11, 13-22), [circa 1844] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A History of the Art of Printing by H. Noel Humphreys, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Stultifera Navis" illustration from A History of the Art of Printing by H. Noel Humphreys, [1868] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified [possibly another edition of A History of the Art of Printing by H. Noel Humphreys], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [illustrations by Darley], 19th century (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - [illustrations of Mexico], 19th century (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Picture of Dorian Gray published by Charles Carrington, Paris., 1908 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - [wild animals] by Howitt, 1798-1799 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - [landscape scenes and maps/diagrams], 1838-1839 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scenes from The Iliad, 19th century (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Scenes from The Odyssey, 19th century (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, including some title pages, 1793-1844 undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- French, Series II
  - [Decoration of St. Chapelle likely from Histoire archéologique, descriptive et graphique de la Sainte-Chapelle du Palais ] (plates 1-11, 13-18), [1857] (Box 2)
  - Livre d'ornements par Lienard., 1866-1872 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Scenes from Moliere plays, 19th century (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scenes from Les Fables de La Fontaine, 19th century (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Illustrations by Boullaire, some of Madame Bovary, 20th century (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Illustrations by Eugene Rodrigues, "Le Jardin de Berenice" final state, 20th century (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Illustrations by Eugene Rodrigues, "Le Jardin de Berenice" early states, 20th century (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Illustrations by Salmon, Madame Bovary, 20th century (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Illustrations by Schmied, 20th century (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - Illustrations by Toulet, 20th century (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Scenes of French life, including the Revolution, 1921 undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Reproductions of artworks, 20th century (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 19th century-20th century (Box 4, Folder 13)
- German, Series III
  - [Interior architectural decoration in color] from Deutsches Maler-Journal, [1877-1881] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gewerbehalle printed by J. Engelhorn, Stuttgart [decorative arts], late 19th century (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Items printed by Julius Hoffmann, Stuttgart [decorative arts], late 19th century (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Plates from Dekorative Vorbilder, printed by J. Hoffmann, [1886-1906] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Plates from Zeitschrift des baner. Kunstgewerbeverein, 1888-1896 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - [plates of military costumes and accessories] published by H. Toussaint & Cie., Berlin., late 19th century (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - [medieval costume], 20th century (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - [churches] published by T. Habicht, Bonn., 19th century (Box 3, Folder 6)